<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title>
    <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University
</description>
    <link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 11:33:56 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 11:33:56 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>SARS-CoV-2 evolution in animals suggests mechanisms for rapid variant selection</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 spillback from humans into domestic and wild animals has been well documented, and an accumulating number of studies illustrate that human-to-animal transmission is widespread in cats, mink, deer, and other species. Experimental inoculations of cats, mink, and ferrets have perpetuated transmission cycles. We sequenced full genomes of Vero cell-expanded SARS-CoV-2 inoculum and viruses recovered from cats (n = 6), dogs (n = 3), hamsters (n = 3), and a ferret (n = 1) following experimental exposure. Five nonsynonymous changes relative to the USA-WA1/2020 prototype strain were near fixation in the stock used for inoculation but had reverted to wild-type sequences at these sites in dogs, cats, and hamsters within 1- to 3-d postexposure. A total of 14 emergent variants (six in nonstructural genes, six in spike, and one each in orf8 and nucleocapsid) were detected in viruses recovered from animals. This included substitutions in spike residues H69, N501, and D614, which also vary in human lineages of concern. Even though a live virus was not cultured from dogs, substitutions in replicase genes were detected in amplified sequences. The rapid selection of SARS-CoV-2 variants in vitro and in vivo reveals residues with functional significance during host switching. These observations also illustrate the potential for spillback from animal hosts to accelerate the evolution of new viral lineages, findings of particular concern for dogs and cats living in households with COVID-19 patients. More generally, this glimpse into viral host switching reveals the unrealized rapidity and plasticity of viral evolution in experimental animal model systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/11/02/Bashor_cats.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/11/02/Bashor_cats.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Audrey Bankes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Audrey is an undergraduate researcher who began in the lab in the fall of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/09/01/audrey-bankes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/09/01/audrey-bankes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kim Awuor Onyango</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Kim is an undergraduate microbiology major who joined the lab to perform directed research in the summer of 2021 as a departmental undergraduate research fellow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/25/kim-onyango.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/25/kim-onyango.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sydney Perkins</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sydney is a CSU undergraduate who performed research in the lab in the summer of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/sydney-perkins.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/sydney-perkins.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brian (Keller) Gonzalez</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Keller is an undergraduate at UC Berkeley who performed research in the lab in the summer of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/keller-gonzalez.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/keller-gonzalez.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Whole Virion Vaccine for COVID-19 Produced via a Novel Inactivation Method and Preliminary Demonstration of Efficacy in an Animal Challenge Model</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has generated intense interest in the rapid development and evaluation of vaccine candidates for this disease and other emerging diseases. Several novel methods for preparing vaccine candidates are currently undergoing clinical evaluation in response to the urgent need to prevent the spread of COVID-19. In many cases, these methods rely on new approaches for vaccine production and immune stimulation. We report on the use of a novel method (SolaVAX) for production of an inactivated vaccine candidate and the testing of that candidate in a hamster animal model for its ability to prevent infection upon challenge with SARS-CoV-2 virus. The studies employed in this work included an evaluation of the levels of neutralizing antibody produced post-vaccination, levels of specific antibody sub-types to RBD and spike protein that were generated, evaluation of viral shedding post-challenge, flow cytometric and single cell sequencing data on cellular fractions and histopathological evaluation of tissues post-challenge. The results from this preliminary evaluation provide insight into the immunological responses occurring as a result of vaccination with the proposed vaccine candidate and the impact that adjuvant formulations, specifically developed to promote Th1 type immune responses, have on vaccine efficacy and protection against infection following challenge with live SARS-CoV-2. This data may have utility in the development of effective vaccine candidates broadly. Furthermore, the results of this preliminary evaluation suggest that preparation of a whole virion vaccine for COVID-19 using this specific photochemical method may have potential utility in the preparation of one such vaccine candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/04/01/Ragan_solavax.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/04/01/Ragan_solavax.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Genomic characterization of 99 viruses from the bunyavirus families Nairoviridae, Peribunyaviridae, and Phenuiviridae, including 35 previously unsequenced viruses</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bunyaviruses (&lt;em&gt;Negarnaviricota: Bunyavirales&lt;/em&gt;) are a large and diverse group of viruses that include important human, veterinary, and plant pathogens. The rapid characterization of known and new emerging pathogens depends on the availability of comprehensive reference sequence databases that can be used to match unknowns, infer evolutionary relationships and pathogenic potential, and make response decisions in an evidence-based manner. In this study, we determined the coding-complete genome sequences of 99 bunyaviruses in the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s Arbovirus Reference Collection, focusing on orthonairoviruses (family &lt;em&gt;Nairoviridae&lt;/em&gt;), orthobunyaviruses (&lt;em&gt;Peribunyaviridae&lt;/em&gt;), and phleboviruses (&lt;em&gt;Phenuiviridae&lt;/em&gt;) that either completely or partially lacked genome sequences. These viruses had been collected over 66 years from 27 countries from vertebrates and arthropods representing 37 genera. Many of the viruses had been characterized serologically and through experimental infection of animals but were isolated in the pre-sequencing era. We took advantage of our unusually large sample size to systematically evaluate genomic characteristics of these viruses, including reassortment, and co-infection. We corroborated our findings using several independent molecular and virologic approaches, including Sanger sequencing of 197 genome segments, and plaque isolation of viruses from putative co-infected virus stocks. This study contributes to the described genetic diversity of bunyaviruses and will enhance the capacity to characterize emerging human pathogenic bunyaviruses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kading and Stenglein corresponding authors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/03/01/Kapuscinski_bunyas.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/03/01/Kapuscinski_bunyas.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In Vitro Reassortment between Endemic Bluetongue Viruses Features Global Shifts in Segment Frequencies and Preferred Segment Combinations</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bunyaviruses (&lt;em&gt;Negarnaviricota: Bunyavirales&lt;/em&gt;) are a large and diverse group of viruses that include important human, veterinary, and plant pathogens. The rapid characterization of known and new emerging pathogens depends on the availability of comprehensive reference sequence databases that can be used to match unknowns, infer evolutionary relationships and pathogenic potential, and make response decisions in an evidence-based manner. In this study, we determined the coding-complete genome sequences of 99 bunyaviruses in the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s Arbovirus Reference Collection, focusing on orthonairoviruses (family &lt;em&gt;Nairoviridae&lt;/em&gt;), orthobunyaviruses (&lt;em&gt;Peribunyaviridae&lt;/em&gt;), and phleboviruses (&lt;em&gt;Phenuiviridae&lt;/em&gt;) that either completely or partially lacked genome sequences. These viruses had been collected over 66 years from 27 countries from vertebrates and arthropods representing 37 genera. Many of the viruses had been characterized serologically and through experimental infection of animals but were isolated in the pre-sequencing era. We took advantage of our unusually large sample size to systematically evaluate genomic characteristics of these viruses, including reassortment, and co-infection. We corroborated our findings using several independent molecular and virologic approaches, including Sanger sequencing of 197 genome segments, and plaque isolation of viruses from putative co-infected virus stocks. This study contributes to the described genetic diversity of bunyaviruses and will enhance the capacity to characterize emerging human pathogenic bunyaviruses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/02/16/Kopanke_reassortment.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/02/16/Kopanke_reassortment.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lexi Keene</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lexi is a PhD student in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmb.colostate.edu/&quot;&gt;Cell and Molecular Biology&lt;/a&gt; graduate program who joined the lab in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/01/01/lexi-keene.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/01/01/lexi-keene.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Serpentovirus (Nidovirus) and Orthoreovirus Coinfection in Captive Veiled Chameleons (Chamaeleo calyptratus) with Respiratory Disease</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serpentoviruses are an emerging group of nidoviruses known to cause respiratory disease in snakes and have been associated with disease in other non-avian reptile species (lizards and turtles). This study describes multiple episodes of respiratory disease-associated mortalities in a collection of juvenile veiled chameleons (Chamaeleo calyptratus). Histopathologic lesions included rhinitis and interstitial pneumonia with epithelial proliferation and abundant mucus. Metagenomic sequencing detected coinfection with two novel serpentoviruses and a novel orthoreovirus. Veiled chameleon serpentoviruses are most closely related to serpentoviruses identified in snakes, lizards, and turtles (approximately 40-50% nucleotide and amino acid identity of ORF1b). Veiled chameleon orthoreovirus is most closely related to reptilian orthoreoviruses identified in snakes (approximately 80-90% nucleotide and amino acid identity of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase). A high prevalence of serpentovirus infection (&amp;gt;80%) was found in clinically healthy subadult and adult veiled chameleons, suggesting the potential for chronic subclinical carriers. Juvenile veiled chameleons typically exhibited a more rapid progression compared to subadults and adults, indicating a possible age association with morbidity and mortality. This is the first description of a serpentovirus infection in any chameleon species. A causal relationship between serpentovirus infection and respiratory disease in chameleons is suspected. The significance of orthoreovirus coinfection remains unknown. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2020/11/24/Hoon-Hanks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2020/11/24/Hoon-Hanks.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
