<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title> <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University </description><link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link> <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 14:18:09 -0700</pubDate> <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 14:18:09 -0700</lastBuildDate> <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator> <item><title>Tillie Dunham</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Tillie is an MIP major performing directed research in the lab on viruses in arthropod model organisms and disease vectors. Tillie started spring semester 2019.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/tillie-dunham.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/tillie-dunham.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Landon Basner</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Landon is an MIP major performing directed research in the lab on bunyaviruses and working in the NGS facility. Landon started spring semester 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/landon-basner.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/landon-basner.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>The expectations and challenges of wildlife disease research in the era of genomics: forecasting with a horizon scan-like exercise</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The outbreak and transmission of disease-causing pathogens are contributing to the unprecedented rate of biodiversity decline. Recent advances in genomics have coalesced into powerful tools to monitor, detect, and reconstruct the role of pathogens impacting wildlife populations. Wildlife researchers are thus uniquely positioned to merge ecological and evolutionary studies with genomic technologies to exploit unprecedented ‘Big Data’ tools in disease research; however, many researchers lack the training and expertise required to use these computationally intensive methodologies. To address this disparity, the inaugural ‘Genomics of Disease in Wildlife’ workshop assembled early to mid-career professionals with expertise across scientific disciplines (e.g., genomics, wildlife biology, veterinary sciences, and conservation management) for training in the application of genomic tools to wildlife disease research. A horizon scanning-like exercise, an activity to identify forthcoming trends and challenges, performed by the workshop participants identified and discussed five themes considered to be the most pressing to the application of genomics in wildlife disease research: i) “Improving Communication”, ii) “Methodological and Analytical Advancements”, iii) “Translation into Practice”, iv) “Integrating Landscape Ecology and Genomics”, and v) “Emerging New Questions”. Wide-ranging solutions from the horizon scan were international in scope, itemized both deficiencies and strengths in wildlife genomic initiatives, promoted the use of genomic technologies to unite wildlife and human disease research, and advocated best practices for optimal use of genomic tools in wildlife disease projects. The results offer a glimpse of the potential revolution in human and wildlife disease research possible through multi-disciplinary collaborations at local, regional, and global scales.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2019/01/12/Fitak_Horizon_Scan.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2019/01/12/Fitak_Horizon_Scan.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Strengthening the Interaction of the Virology Community with the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) by Linking Virus Names and Their Abbreviations to Virus Species</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) is tasked with classifying viruses into taxa (phyla to species) and devising taxon names. Virus names and virus name abbreviations are currently not within the ICTV’s official remit and are not regulated by an official entity. Many scientists, medical/veterinary professionals, and regulatory agencies do not address evolutionary questions nor are they concerned with the hierarchical organization of the viral world, and therefore, have limited use for ICTV-devised taxa. Instead, these professionals look to the ICTV as an expert point source that provides the most current taxonomic affiliations of viruses of interests to facilitate document writing. These needs are currently unmet as an ICTV-supported, easily searchable database that includes all published virus names and abbreviations linked to their taxa is not available. In addition, in stark contrast to other biological taxonomic frameworks, virus taxonomy currently permits individual species to have several members. Consequently, confusion emerges among those who are not aware of the difference between taxa and viruses, and because certain well-known viruses cannot be located in ICTV publications or be linked to their species. In addition, the number of duplicate names and abbreviations has increased dramatically in the literature. To solve this conundrum, the ICTV could mandate listing all viruses of established species and all reported unclassified viruses in forthcoming online ICTV Reports and create a searchable webpage using this information. The International Union of Microbiology Societies could also consider changing the mandate of the ICTV to include the nomenclature of all viruses in addition to taxon considerations. With such a mandate expansion, official virus names and virus name abbreviations could be catalogued and virus nomenclature could be standardized. As a result, the ICTV would become an even more useful resource for all stakeholders in virology.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/31/Calisher_virus_names.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/31/Calisher_virus_names.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>A reverse-transcription/RNase H based protocol for depletion of mosquito ribosomal RNA facilitates viral intrahost evolution analysis, transcriptomics and pathogen discovery.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identifying novel viruses or assessing viral variation by NGS requires high sequencing coverage. More than 90% of total RNA is ribosomal (rRNA), making variant calling, virus discovery or transcriptomic profiling difficult. Current methods to increase informative reads suffer from drawbacks, either they cannot be used for some viruses, are optimized for a single species, or introduce bias. We describe a two-part approach combining reverse-transcription to create RNA/DNA hybrids which are then degraded with RNaseH/DNase sequentially that works for three medically relevant mosquito genera; Aedes, Anopheles, and Culex. We demonstrate depletion of rRNA from different samples, including whole mosquitoes and midgut contents from FTA cards. We describe novel insect-specific virus genomes from field collected mosquitoes. The protocol requires only common laboratory reagents and small oligonucleotides specific to rRNA. This approach can be adapted for other organisms, aiding virus diversity analyses, virus discovery and transcriptomics in both laboratory and field samples.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/30/Fauver_RNaseH.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/30/Fauver_RNaseH.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Ebola virus, but not Marburg virus, replicates efficiently and without required adaptation in snake cells.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ebola virus (EBOV) disease is a viral hemorrhagic fever with a high case-fatality rate in humans. This disease is caused by four members of the filoviral genus Ebolavirus, including EBOV. The natural hosts reservoirs of ebolaviruses remain to be identified. Glycoprotein 2 of reptarenaviruses, known to infect only boa constrictors and pythons, is similar in sequence and structure to ebolaviral glycoprotein 2, suggesting that EBOV may be able to infect reptilian cells. Therefore, we serially passaged EBOV and a distantly related filovirus, Marburg virus (MARV), in boa constrictor JK cells and characterized viral infection/replication and mutational frequency by confocal imaging and sequencing. We observed that EBOV efficiently infected and replicated in JK cells, but MARV did not. In contrast to most cell lines, EBOV-infected JK cells did not result in an obvious cytopathic effect. Surprisingly, genomic characterization of serial-passaged EBOV in JK cells revealed that genomic adaptation was not required for infection. Deep sequencing coverage (&amp;gt;10,000×) demonstrated the existence of only a single nonsynonymous variant (EBOV glycoprotein precursor pre-GP T544I) of unknown significance within the viral population that exhibited a shift in frequency of at least 10 per cent over six serial passages. In summary, we present the first reptilian cell line that replicates a filovirus at high titers, and for the first time demonstrate a filovirus genus-specific restriction to MARV in a cell line. Our data suggest the possibility that there may be differences between the natural host spectra of ebolaviruses and marburgviruses.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/11/28/Fedewa_Ebola.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/11/28/Fedewa_Ebola.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Co-Infection Patterns in Individual Ixodes scapularis Ticks Reveal Associations between Viral, Eukaryotic and Bacterial Microorganisms</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ixodes scapularis&lt;/em&gt; ticks harbor a variety of microorganisms, including eukaryotes, bacteria and viruses. Some of these can be transmitted to and cause disease in humans and other vertebrates. Others are not pathogenic, but may impact the ability of the tick to harbor and transmit pathogens. A growing number of studies have examined the influence of bacteria on tick vector competence but the influence of the tick virome remains less clear, despite a surge in the discovery of tick-associated viruses. In this study, we performed shotgun RNA sequencing on 112 individual adult &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis&lt;/em&gt; collected in Wisconsin, USA. We characterized the abundance, prevalence and co-infection rates of viruses, bacteria and eukaryotic microorganisms. We identified pairs of tick-infecting microorganisms whose observed co-infection rates were higher or lower than would be expected, or whose RNA levels were positively correlated in co-infected ticks. Many of these co-occurrence and correlation relationships involved two bunyaviruses, South Bay virus and blacklegged tick phlebovirus-1. These viruses were also the most prevalent microorganisms in the ticks we sampled, and had the highest average RNA levels. Evidence of associations between microbes included a positive correlation between RNA levels of South Bay virus and &lt;em&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/em&gt;, the Lyme disease agent. These findings contribute to the rationale for experimental studies on the impact of viruses on tick biology and vector competence.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/07/22/Cross_tick_metagenome.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/07/22/Cross_tick_metagenome.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Adventitious viruses persistently infect three commonly used mosquito cell lines.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mosquito cell lines have been used extensively in research to isolate and propagate arthropod-borne viruses and understand virus-vector interactions. Despite their utility as an in vitro tool, these cell lines are poorly defined and may harbor insect-specific viruses. Accordingly, we screened four commonly-used mosquito cell lines, C6/36 and U4.4 cells from Aedes albopictus, Aag2 cells from Aedes aegypti, and Hsu cells from Culex quinquefasciatus, for the presence of adventitious (i.e. exogenous) viruses. All four cell lines stained positive for double-stranded RNA, indicative of RNA virus replication. We subsequently identified viruses infecting Aag2, U4.4 and Hsu cell lines using untargeted next-generation sequencing, but not C6/36 cells. PCR confirmation revealed that these sequences stem from active viral replication and/or integration into the cellular genome. Our results show that these commonly-used mosquito cell lines are persistently-infected with several viruses. This finding may be critical to interpreting data generated in these systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/06/26/Weger-Lucarelli_mosquito_cell_viruses.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/06/26/Weger-Lucarelli_mosquito_cell_viruses.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Xenosurveillance reflects traditional sampling techniques for the identification of human pathogens: A comparative study in West Africa</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;BACKGROUND:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Novel surveillance strategies are needed to detect the rapid and continuous emergence of infectious disease agents. Ideally, new sampling strategies should be simple to implement, technologically uncomplicated, and applicable to areas where emergence events are known to occur. To this end, xenosurveillance is a technique that makes use of blood collected by hematophagous arthropods to monitor and identify vertebrate pathogens. Mosquitoes are largely ubiquitous animals that often exist in sizable populations. As well, many domestic or peridomestic species of mosquitoes will preferentially take blood-meals from humans, making them a unique and largely untapped reservoir to collect human blood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="methodologyprincipal-findings"&gt;METHODOLOGY/PRINCIPAL FINDINGS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;We sought to take advantage of this phenomenon by systematically collecting blood-fed mosquitoes during a field trail in Northern Liberia to determine whether pathogen sequences from blood engorged mosquitoes accurately mirror those obtained directly from humans. Specifically, blood was collected from humans via finger-stick and by aspirating bloodfed mosquitoes from the inside of houses. Shotgun metagenomic sequencing of RNA and DNA derived from these specimens was performed to detect pathogen sequences. Samples obtained from xenosurveillance and from finger-stick blood collection produced a similar number and quality of reads aligning to two human viruses, GB virus C and hepatitis B virus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="conclusionssignificance"&gt;CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;This study represents the first systematic comparison between xenosurveillance and more traditional sampling methodologies, while also demonstrating the viability of xenosurveillance as a tool to sample human blood for circulating pathogens.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/03/21/Fauver_xenosurveillance.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/03/21/Fauver_xenosurveillance.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Divergent bornaviruses from Australian carpet pythons with neurological disease date the origin of extant Bornaviridae prior to the end-Cretaceous extinction.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tissue samples from Australian carpet pythons (Morelia spilota) with neurological disease were screened for viruses using next-generation sequencing. Coding complete genomes of two bornaviruses were identified with the gene order 3’-N-X-P-G-M-L, representing a transposition of the G and M genes compared to other bornaviruses and most mononegaviruses. Use of these viruses to search available vertebrate genomes enabled recognition of further endogenous bornavirus-like elements (EBLs) in diverse placental mammals, including humans. Codivergence patterns and shared integration sites revealed an ancestral laurasiatherian EBLG integration (77 million years ago [MYA]) and a previously identified afrotherian EBLG integration (83 MYA). The novel python bornaviruses clustered more closely with these EBLs than with other exogenous bornaviruses, suggesting that these viruses diverged from previously known bornaviruses prior to the end-Cretaceous (K-Pg) extinction, 66 MYA. It is possible that EBLs protected mammals from ancient bornaviral disease, providing a selective advantage in the recovery from the K-Pg extinction. A degenerate PCR primer set was developed to detect a highly conserved region of the bornaviral polymerase gene. It was used to detect 15 more genetically distinct bornaviruses from Australian pythons that represent a group that is likely to contain a number of novel species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="author-summary"&gt;Author summary&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike plants and animals, viruses don’t leave fossilised remains that can be used to study their ancient history. Rarely, however, some virus sequences end up as integrated copies in host genomes. These ‘fossilised’ virus sequences provide a window into virus evolution on a geological time scale. In this study, we identified bornaviruses in pythons, some of which had neurological disease. Bornaviruses have been associated with persistent neurological infections in a variety of mammalian and avian hosts. Here, we reveal that bornaviruses are associated with similar disease in reptiles as well. These new snake viruses turned out to be most closely related to bornavirus-like sequences that integrated into the DNA of mammals prior to the major extinction event at the end of the age of dinosaurs, the end-Cretaceous (K-Pg) extinction, 66 million years ago, allowing us to infer details of their prehistoric evolutionary history and origin. We also developed a test to detect these viruses from samples collected from live snakes, and used it to identify more related snake bornaviruses, indicating that this group will likely continue to expand.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/02/20/Hyndman_bornavirus.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/02/20/Hyndman_bornavirus.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> </channel> </rss>