<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title> <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University </description><link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link> <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 15:42:02 -0700</pubDate> <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 15:42:02 -0700</lastBuildDate> <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator> <item><title>Respiratory disease in ball pythons (Python regius) experimentally infected with ball python nidovirus</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Circumstantial evidence has linked a new group of nidoviruses with respiratory disease in pythons, lizards, and cattle. We conducted experimental infections in ball pythons (Python regius) to test the hypothesis that ball python nidovirus (BPNV) infection results in respiratory disease. Three ball pythons were inoculated orally and intratracheally with cell culture isolated BPNV and two were sham inoculated. Antemortem choanal, oroesophageal, and cloacal swabs and postmortem tissues of infected snakes were positive for viral RNA, protein, and infectious virus by qRT-PCR, immunohistochemistry, western blot and virus isolation. Clinical signs included oral mucosal reddening, abundant mucus secretions, open-mouthed breathing, and anorexia. Histologic lesions included chronic-active mucinous rhinitis, stomatitis, tracheitis, esophagitis and proliferative interstitial pneumonia. Control snakes remained negative and free of clinical signs throughout the experiment. Our findings establish a causal relationship between nidovirus infection and respiratory disease in ball pythons and shed light on disease progression and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="importance"&gt;Importance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past several years, nidovirus infection has been circumstantially linked to fatal respiratory disease in multiple python species, but a causal relationship has not been definitively established. Through experimental infections, our study fulfills Koch’s postulates and confirms ball python nidovirus as a primary respiratory pathogen in this species. Our findings will provide veterinarians valuable information for the diagnosis and management of this disease and lay the groundwork for continued scientific investigation of this sometimes fatal disease. Python nidoviruses are members of a growing group of viruses that have been associated with severe respiratory disease, including bovine nidovirus and shingleback lizard nidovirus. The establishment of BPNV as a primary pathogen in pythons is an important step in understanding the pathogenic potential of this emerging group of viruses.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/01/11/Hoon-Hanks_nidovirus.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/01/11/Hoon-Hanks_nidovirus.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Metagenomic Investigation of Idiopathic Meningoencephalomyelitis in Dogs</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;BACKGROUND:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meningoencephalomyelitis of unknown origin (MUO) is a common and life-threatening neuroinflammatory disease in dogs. Features of the disease are suggestive of an underlying immune-mediated process, but the association of this disease with a pathogen is still unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="hypothesisobjectives"&gt;HYPOTHESIS/OBJECTIVES:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;To search for candidate etiologic agent associated with cases if MUO using next generation metagenomic sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="animals"&gt;ANIMALS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Twenty-two dogs diagnosed with either MUO (11/22; 10 CSF and 3 brain), or noninflammatory CNS diseases inconsistent with MUO (11/22; 11 CSF and 2 brain) that served as negative controls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="methods"&gt;METHODS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;A case control study was performed by identifying MUO and non-MUO cases. Samples were blindly processed and then unblinded for comparative analyses. Inclusion criteria for MUO cases included consistent MRI lesions and inflammatory CSF with a negative PCR panel for infectious agents or histopathologic diagnosis. Dogs with glucocorticoid therapy within 2 weeks of sample collection were excluded. Fresh-frozen cerebrospinal fluid (CSF; 21) and brain (5) samples were collected and RNA and DNA were extracted separately for shotgun metagenomic sequencing. Known positive samples were used as controls to validate our sequencing and analysis pipelines and to establish limits of detection. Sequencing results were analyzed at a nucleotide and protein level for broad comparison to known infectious organisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="results"&gt;RESULTS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;No candidate etiologic agents were identified in dogs with MUO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="conclusions-and-clinical-importance"&gt;CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL IMPORTANCE:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;These results support but do not prove the hypothesis that MUO is not associated with infectious agents and might be an autoimmune disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was a result of a great collaboration with veterinary neurologist &lt;a href="http://www.csuvth.colostate.edu/DirectorySearch/Search/MemberProfile/vth/1701/McGrath/Stephanie"&gt;Stephanie McGrath&lt;/a&gt;, who is a co-corresponding author.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/12/02/Hoon-Hanks_MUO.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/12/02/Hoon-Hanks_MUO.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Modeling the evolution of SIV sooty mangabey progenitor virus towards HIV-2 using humanized mice</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV-2 is thought to have originated from an SIV progenitor native to sooty mangabeys. To model the initial human transmission and understand the sequential viral evolution, humanized mice were infected with SIVsm and serially passaged for five generations. Productive infection was seen by week 3 during the initial challenge followed by chronic viremia and gradual CD4+ T cell decline. Viral loads increased by the 5th generation resulting in more rapid CD4+ T cell decline. Genetic analysis revealed several amino acid substitutions that were nonsynonymous and fixed in multiple hu-mice across each of the 5 generations in the nef, env and rev regions. The highest rate of substitution occurred in the nef and env regions and most were observed within the first two generations. These data demonstrated the utility of hu-mice in modeling the SIVsm transmission to the human and to evaluate its potential sequential evolution into a human pathogen of HIV-2 lineage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;I assisted with data analysis for this work from the Akkina lab.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/10/01/Schmitt_SIV.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/10/01/Schmitt_SIV.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Lauren Kleine</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Lauren is an undergraduate student in the Biology department. Lauren started working in the lab in the Fall of 2017, and is focusing on computational projects.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/15/lauren-kleine.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/15/lauren-kleine.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Bernadette Maertens</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Bernadette is a student in the MIP &lt;a href="http://csu-cvmbs.colostate.edu/academics/mip/graduate/Pages/microbiology-immunology-professional-masters.aspx"&gt;MS-B professional masters program&lt;/a&gt;. Bernadette started working in the lab in the Fall of 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/11/bernadette-maertens.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/11/bernadette-maertens.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Amy Fox</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Amy is a student in the MIP &lt;a href="http://csu-cvmbs.colostate.edu/academics/mip/graduate/Pages/Microbiology-MS-and-PhD-Program.aspx"&gt;PhD program&lt;/a&gt; who rotated in the lab in the fall of 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/01/amy-fox.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/01/amy-fox.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Genomics of Disease in Wildlife Workshop, 2017</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://github.com/stenglein-lab/2017_GDW/"&gt;Link to workshop material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gdwworkshop.colostate.edu/media/sites/131/2016/11/GDW.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be participating in the inaugural &lt;a href="http://gdwworkshop.colostate.edu/"&gt;Genomics of Disease in Wildlife Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, which is being held starting today at Colorado State University. We just had our kick off reception, and I’m very impressed by the other instructors and the workshop participants. It seems like a great group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be leading several of the sections, on genomics, sequencing, accessing online resources, de novo assembly, and metagenomics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m putting all of the material (lectures, exercises) I’ve developed for this workshop up on GitHub, &lt;a href="http://github.com/stenglein-lab/2017_GDW/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/06/03/GDW_2017.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/06/03/GDW_2017.html</guid> <category>blog</category> </item> <item><title>Zach Osterholz</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Zach is a DVM student from the University of Illinois who worked in the lab in the summer of 2017 as a NIH-funded trainee in the Veterinary Summer Scholars Program. Zach setup our lab to work with live ticks, and performed pilot experiments investigating tick susceptibility to viral infection.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/zach-osterholz.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/zach-osterholz.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Mark Parlier</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Mark is a DVM student at CSU who started working in the lab in the summer of 2017 as a Merial scholar in the Veterinary Summer Scholars Program.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/mark-parlier.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/mark-parlier.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Differential disease susceptibility in experimentally reptarenavirus infected boa constrictors and ball pythons</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inclusion body disease (IBD) is an infectious disease originally described in captive snakes. It has traditionally been diagnosed by the presence of large eosinophilic cytoplasmic inclusions, and is associated with neurological, gastrointestinal and lymphoproliferative disorders. Previously, we identified and established a culture system for a novel lineage of arenaviruses isolated from boa constrictors diagnosed with IBD. Although ample circumstantial evidence suggested that these viruses, now known as reptarenaviruses, cause IBD, there has been no formal demonstration of disease causality since their discovery. We therefore conducted a long-term challenge experiment to test the hypothesis that reptarenaviruses cause IBD. We infected boa constrictors and ball pythons by cardiac injection of purified virus. We monitored progression of viral growth in tissues, blood, and environmental samples. Infection produced dramatically different disease outcomes in snakes of the two species. Ball pythons infected with Golden Gate virus (GoGV) and with another reptarenavirus displayed severe neurological signs within two months and viral replication was only detected in central nervous system tissues. In contrast, GoGV-infected boa constrictors remained free of clinical signs for two years despite high viral loads and the accumulation of large intracellular inclusions in multiple tissues including the brain. Inflammation was associated with infection in ball pythons but not in boa constrictors. Thus, reptarenavirus infection produces inclusions and inclusion body disease, although inclusions per se are neither necessarily associated with nor required for disease. Although the natural distribution of reptarenaviruses has yet to be described, the different outcome of infection may reflect differences in geographical origin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANCE New DNA sequencing technologies have made it easier than ever to identify the sequences of microorganisms in diseased tissues, i.e. to identify organisms that appear to cause disease. But to be certain that a candidate pathogen actually causes disease, it is necessary to provide additional evidence of causality. We have done this to demonstrate that reptarenaviruses cause inclusion body disease (IBD), a serious transmissible disease of snakes. We infected boa constrictors and ball pythons with purified reptarenavirus. Ball pythons fell ill within two months of infection and displayed signs of neurological disease typical of IBD. In contrast, boa constrictors remained healthy over two years despite high levels of virus throughout their bodies. This difference matches previous reports that pythons are more susceptible to IBD than boas and could reflect the possibility that boas are natural hosts of these viruses in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h4&gt;</description> <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/05/16/Stenglein_IBD.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/05/16/Stenglein_IBD.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> </channel> </rss>