<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title>
    <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University
</description>
    <link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 17:07:14 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 17:07:14 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Case for Studying New Viruses of New Hosts.</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virology has largely focused on viruses that are pathogenic to humans or to the other species that we care most about. There is no doubt that this has been a worthwhile investment. But many transformative advances have been made through the in-depth study of relatively obscure viruses that do not appear on lists of prioritized pathogens. In this review, I highlight the benefits that can accrue from the study of viruses and hosts off the beaten track. I take stock of viral sequence diversity across host taxa as an estimate of the bias that exists in our understanding of host-virus interactions. I describe the gains that have been made through the metagenomic discovery of thousands of new viruses in previously unsampled hosts as well as the limitations of metagenomic surveys. I conclude by suggesting that the study of viruses that naturally infect existing and emerging model organisms represents an opportunity to push virology forward in useful and hard to predict ways.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/06/07/Stenglein_annual_review.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/06/07/Stenglein_annual_review.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Occurrence of Wheat Curl Mite and Mite-Vectored Viruses of Wheat in Colorado and Insights into the Wheat Virome</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wheat curl mite (WCM) is a vector of three important wheat viruses in the U.S. Great Plains, wheat streak mosaic virus (WSMV), triticum mosaic virus (TriMV), and High Plains wheat mosaic virus (HPWMoV). This study was conducted to determine the current profile of WCM and WCM-transmitted viruses of wheat and their occurrence in Colorado, including novel wheat viruses via virome analysis. There was a high rate of virus incidence in symptomatic wheat samples collected in 2019 (95%) and 2020 (77%). Single infection of WSMV was most common in both years followed by coinfection with WSMV + TriMV and WSMV + HPWMoV. Both Type 1 and Type 2 mite genotypes were found in Colorado. There was high genetic diversity of WSMV and HPWMoV isolates, whereas TriMV isolates showed minimal sequence variation. Analysis of WSMV isolates revealed novel virus variants including one isolate from a variety trial, where severe disease symptoms were observed on wheat varieties carrying Wsm2, a known virus resistance loci. Virome analysis identified between two to four sequence variants of all eight RNA segments of HPWMoV, which suggests co-occurrence of multiple genotypes within host populations and presence of a possibly novel variant of HPWMoV. A possible novel virus, Tombusviridae sp. and several mycoviruses were identified. Overall, the data presented here highlights the need to define the effect of novel WCM-transmitted virus variants on disease severity, as well as the role of novel viruses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image credit:&lt;/strong&gt;  Simon Waldherr, CC-SA-3.0, &lt;a href=&quot;https://500px.com/photo/219038809/wheat-by-simon-waldherr&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/02/23/Albrecht_wheat_virome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/02/23/Albrecht_wheat_virome.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bluetongue Research at a Crossroads. Modern Genomics Tools Can Pave the Way to New Insights</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluetongue virus (BTV) is an arthropod-borne, segmented double-stranded RNA virus that can cause severe disease in both wild and domestic ruminants. BTV evolves via several key mechanisms, including the accumulation of mutations over time and the reassortment of genome segments.Additionally, BTV must maintain fitness in two disparate hosts, the insect vector and the ruminant. The specific features of viral adaptation in each host that permit host-switching are poorly characterized. Limited field studies and experimental work have alluded to the presence of these phenomena at work, but our understanding of the factors that drive or constrain BTV&amp;#39;s genetic diversification remains incomplete. Current research leveraging novel approaches and whole genome sequencing applications promises to improve our understanding of BTV&amp;#39;s evolution, ultimately contributing to the development of better predictive models and management strategies to reduce future impacts of bluetongue epizootics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/02/15/Kopanke_BTV_review.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/02/15/Kopanke_BTV_review.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Seasonal Dynamics of Mosquito-Borne Viruses in the Southwestern Florida Everglades</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosquitoes were collected for 12 consecutive months beginning June 2016, from 11 locations in the Florida Everglades, Collier County, and tested for viruses by isolation in Vero cells and subsequent identification. One species complex and 31 species of mosquitoes were identified from 668,809 specimens. Ochlerotatus taeniorhynchus comprised 72.2% of the collection. Other notable species were Anopheles crucians complex, Culex nigripalpus, Cx. erraticus, and Cx. cedecei. Seven species of virus were identified from 110 isolations: Everglades, Gumbo Limbo, Mahogany Hammock, Pahayokee, Shark River, Tensaw, and West Nile viruses. Everglades, West Nile, Tensaw, and Mahogany Hammock viruses were most frequently isolated. Largest numbers of viruses were identified from Cx. cedecei, Cx. nigripalpus, and An. crucians complex. Five species of virus were isolated from Cx. cedecei. Viruses were isolated from mangrove, cypress swamp, hardwood hammock, and sawgrass habitats. West Nile virus was isolated August through October when Cx. nigripalpus was most abundant. Everglades virus was the most frequently isolated virus from nine species of mosquitoes collected from June through August. Tensaw virus was isolated primarily from Anopheles species. Isolations were made in July, August, January, February, and April, suggesting that this virus may be present in host-seeking mosquitoes throughout the year. Mahogany Hammock, Shark River, Gumbo Limbo, and Pahayokee viruses were isolated primarily from Cx. cedecei from June through December. Shotgun metagenomic sequencing was used to document that seven pools of Cx. cedecei were infected with two arboviruses. As communities expand into the Everglades, more humans will become exposed to arboviruses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/01/10/Anderson_everglades.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2022/01/10/Anderson_everglades.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Safety study of Rift Valley Fever human vaccine candidate (DDVax) in mosquitoes.</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rift Valley fever virus (RVFV) is a mosquito-borne pathogen with significant human and veterinary health consequences that periodically emerges in epizootics. RVFV causes fetal loss and death in ruminants and in humans can lead to liver and renal disease, delayed-onset encephalitis, retinitis, and in some cases severe haemorrhagic fever. A live attenuated vaccine candidate (DDVax), was developed by the deletion of the virulence factors NSs and NSm from a clinical isolate, ZH501, and has proven safe and immunogenic in rodents, pregnant sheep and non-human primates. Deletion of NSm also severely restricted mosquito midgut infection and inhibited vector-borne transmission. To demonstrate environmental safety, this study investigated the replication, dissemination and transmission efficiency of DDVax in mosquitoes following oral exposure compared to RVFV strains MP-12 and ZH501. Infection and dissemination profiles were also measured in mosquitoes 7 days after they fed on goats inoculated with DDvax or MP-12. We hypothesized that DDVax would infect mosquitoes at significantly lower rates than other RVFV strains and, due to lack of NSm, be transmission incompetent. Exposure of Ae. aegypti and Cx. tarsalis to 8 log10 plaque forming units (PFU)/ml DDVax by artificial bloodmeal resulted in significantly reduced DDVax infection rates in mosquito bodies compared to controls. Plaque assays indicated negligible transmission of infectious DDVax in Cx. tarsalis saliva (1/140 sampled) and none in Ae. aegypti saliva (0/120). Serum from goats inoculated with DDVax or MP-12 did not harbour detectable infectious virus by plaque assay at 1, 2 or 3 days post-inoculation. Infectious virus was, however, recovered from Aedes and Culex bodies that fed on goats vaccinated with MP-12 (13.8% and 4.6%, respectively), but strikingly, DDvax-positive mosquito bodies were greatly reduced (4%, and 0%, respectively). Furthermore, DDVax did not disseminate to legs/wings in any of the goat-fed mosquitoes. Collectively, these results are consistent with a beneficial environmental safety profile.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/12/10/Campbell_DDVax.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/12/10/Campbell_DDVax.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SARS-CoV-2 evolution in animals suggests mechanisms for rapid variant selection</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 spillback from humans into domestic and wild animals has been well documented, and an accumulating number of studies illustrate that human-to-animal transmission is widespread in cats, mink, deer, and other species. Experimental inoculations of cats, mink, and ferrets have perpetuated transmission cycles. We sequenced full genomes of Vero cell-expanded SARS-CoV-2 inoculum and viruses recovered from cats (n = 6), dogs (n = 3), hamsters (n = 3), and a ferret (n = 1) following experimental exposure. Five nonsynonymous changes relative to the USA-WA1/2020 prototype strain were near fixation in the stock used for inoculation but had reverted to wild-type sequences at these sites in dogs, cats, and hamsters within 1- to 3-d postexposure. A total of 14 emergent variants (six in nonstructural genes, six in spike, and one each in orf8 and nucleocapsid) were detected in viruses recovered from animals. This included substitutions in spike residues H69, N501, and D614, which also vary in human lineages of concern. Even though a live virus was not cultured from dogs, substitutions in replicase genes were detected in amplified sequences. The rapid selection of SARS-CoV-2 variants in vitro and in vivo reveals residues with functional significance during host switching. These observations also illustrate the potential for spillback from animal hosts to accelerate the evolution of new viral lineages, findings of particular concern for dogs and cats living in households with COVID-19 patients. More generally, this glimpse into viral host switching reveals the unrealized rapidity and plasticity of viral evolution in experimental animal model systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/11/02/Bashor_cats.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2021/11/02/Bashor_cats.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Audrey Bankes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Audrey is an undergraduate researcher who began in the lab in the fall of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/09/01/audrey-bankes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/09/01/audrey-bankes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kim Awuor Onyango</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Kim was an undergraduate microbiology major who joined the lab to perform directed research in the summer of 2021 as a departmental undergraduate research fellow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/25/kim-onyango.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/25/kim-onyango.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sydney Perkins</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sydney is a CSU undergraduate who performed research in the lab in the summer of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/sydney-perkins.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/sydney-perkins.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brian (Keller) Gonzalez</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Keller is an undergraduate at UC Berkeley who performed research in the lab in the summer of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/keller-gonzalez.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2021/05/01/keller-gonzalez.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
