<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title>
    <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University
</description>
    <link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 19:23:23 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 19:23:23 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lauren Obrien</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lauren is an undergraduate researcher who began in the lab in the spring of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;image (icon) credit: James Keuning, public domain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenounproject.com/icon/scientist-10278/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/04/01/lauren-obrien.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/04/01/lauren-obrien.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Julia Mitchell</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Julia is an undergraduate researcher who began in the lab in the spring of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;image (icon) credit: Iconathon, public domain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenounproject.com/icon/scientist-2909361/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/03/28/julia-mitchell.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/03/28/julia-mitchell.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brett Moehn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Brett is a PhD student in the Microbiology, Immunology, and Pathology PhD Program who joined the lab in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;image (icon) credit: Antonis Makriyannis, public domain.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenounproject.com/icon/scientist-11404/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/02/19/brett-moehn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/02/19/brett-moehn.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charli Geer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Charli is a PhD student in the Cell and Molecular Biology Program who joined the lab in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/02/13/charli-geer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2024/02/13/charli-geer.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>team</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assessing Reassortment between Bluetongue Virus Serotypes 10 and 17 at Different Coinfection Ratios in Culicoides sonorenesis</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluetongue virus (BTV) is a segmented, double-stranded RNA orbivirus listed by the World Organization for Animal Health and transmitted by Culicoides biting midges. Segmented viruses can reassort, which facilitates rapid and important genotypic changes. Our study evaluated reassortment in Culicoides sonorensis midges coinfected with different ratios of BTV-10 and BTV-17. Midges were fed blood containing BTV-10, BTV-17, or a combination of both serotypes at 90:10, 75:25, 50:50, 25:75, or 10:90 ratios. Midges were collected every other day and tested for infection using pan BTV and cox1 (housekeeping gene) qRT-PCR. A curve was fit to the ∆Ct values (pan BTV Ct-cox1 Ct) for each experimental group. On day 10, the midges were processed for BTV plaque isolation. Genotypes of the plaques were determined by next-generation sequencing. Pairwise comparison of ∆Ct curves demonstrated no differences in viral RNA levels between coinfected treatment groups. Plaque genotyping indicated that most plaques fully aligned with one of the parental strains; however, reassortants were detected, and in the 75:25 pool, most plaques were reassortant. Reassortant prevalence may be maximized upon the occurrence of reassortant genotypes that can outcompete the parental genotypes. BTV reassortment and resulting biological consequences are important elements to understanding orbivirus emergence and evolution. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2024/02/02/Carpenter_reassortment_ratios.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2024/02/02/Carpenter_reassortment_ratios.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Draft genome sequence of Planococcus sp. SK3692</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole-genome sequencing was performed for a Planococcus sp. isolate.  This bacterium was of interest because of its vibrant orange pigmentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image credit: Dog in Silhouette on Ocean Beach SF, Ingrid V Taylar, CC-BY-2.0 DEED, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/taylar/52528907765/&quot;&gt;link to original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2024/01/17/Kiehl_Planococcus_genome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2024/01/17/Kiehl_Planococcus_genome.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Whole-genome sequence of Paenibacillus sp., isolated from soil, Fort Collins, Colorado, USA</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A whole genome sequence of a Paenibacillus sp. bacterium isolated from soil in Fort Collins, Colorado was obtained. This bacterium was of particular interest due to its antibiotic potential against Gram-positive pathogen surrogates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Image credit: A colony generated by the Branching (Tip splitting) morphotype bacteria of P. dendritiformis. The image was taken in Prof. Ben-Jacob&amp;#39;s lab, Tel-Aviv University, Israel.  CC-BY-SA-3.0.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Paenibacillus_dendritiformis_colony.png&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/10/19/Kiehl_Paenibacillus_genome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/10/19/Kiehl_Paenibacillus_genome.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assessing shared respiratory pathogens between domestic (Ovis aries) and bighorn (Ovis canadensis) sheep; methods for multiplex PCR, amplicon sequencing, and bioinformatics to characterize respiratory flora</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respiratory disease is responsible for dramatic population declines in bighorn sheep (&lt;em&gt;Ovis canadensis&lt;/em&gt;), and respiratory pathogen diagnostics contribute to the management of bighorn populations. To create a comprehensive and consistent approach to bighorn sheep respiratory diagnostics, we created a culture-independent assay to detect and strain type &lt;em&gt;Mannheimia haemolytica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bibersteinia trehalosi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pasteurella multocida&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Mycoplasma ovipneumoniae&lt;/em&gt;. The assay also detects and characterizes the &lt;em&gt;Pasteurellaceae&lt;/em&gt; leukotoxin A gene, and broadly assesses the bacterial composition of each sample based on 16S rRNA sequences. The assay is based on a three-step approach: 1) Multiplex PCR to amplify targets including eight loci for each bacterial species, the &lt;em&gt;Pasteurellaceae lktA&lt;/em&gt; gene, and the 16S rRNA gene 2) Library preparation, barcoding, and short-read Illumina sequencing to determine the genetic sequences of each target, and 3) Bioinformatics in the form of automated software to analyze genetic sequences. The assay was designed to assess shared pathogens between domestic and bighorn sheep, but could be useful for many applications in bighorn sheep respiratory disease research and management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Image credit: Bighorn Sheep Ram, USFWS Mountain-Prairie, Public Domain, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/usfwsmtnprairie/49727914073&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/10/19/Fox_sheep_respiratory_pathogens.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/10/19/Fox_sheep_respiratory_pathogens.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evaluation of Vector-Enabled Xenosurveillance in Rural Guatemala</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveillance methods that permit rapid detection of circulating pathogens in low-resource settings are desperately needed. In this study, we evaluated a mosquito bloodmeal-based surveillance method (“xenosurveillance”) in rural Guatemala. Twenty households from two villages (Los Encuentros and Chiquirines) in rural southwest Guatemala were enrolled and underwent weekly prospective surveillance from August 2019 to December 2019 (16 weeks). When febrile illness was reported in a household, recently blood-fed mosquitoes were collected from within dwellings and blood samples taken from each member of the household. Mosquitoes were identified to species and blood sources identified by sequencing. Shotgun metagenomic sequencing was used to identify circulating viruses. &lt;em&gt;Culex pipiens&lt;/em&gt; (60.9%) and &lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/em&gt; (18.6%) were the most abundant mosquitoes collected. Bloodmeal sources were most commonly human (32.6%) and chicken (31.6%), with various other mammal and avian hosts detected. Several mosquito-specific viruses were detected, including &lt;em&gt;Culex&lt;/em&gt; orthophasma virus. Human pathogens were not detected. Therefore, xenosurveillance may require more intensive sampling to detect human pathogens in Guatemala and ecologically similar localities in Central America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Image credit: US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Mosquito Image Library, public domain, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/mosquitoes/gallery/culex/index.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/10/16/McMinn_xenosurveillance_Guatemala.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/10/16/McMinn_xenosurveillance_Guatemala.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In Situ Hybridization (RNAscope) Detection of Bluetongue Virus Serotypes 10 and 17 in Experimentally Co-Infected Culicoides sonorensis</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluetongue virus (BTV) is a segmented, double-stranded RNA virus transmitted by &lt;em&gt;Culicoides&lt;/em&gt; biting midges. Infection of domestic and wild ruminants with BTV can result in a devastating disease and significant economic losses. As a virus with a segmented genome, reassortment among the BTV serotypes that have co-infected a host may increase genetic diversity, which can alter BTV transmission dynamics and generate epizootic events. The objective of this study was to determine the extent of dissemination and characterize the tropism of BTV serotypes 10 and 17 in co-infected &lt;em&gt;Culicoides sonorensis&lt;/em&gt;. Midges were exposed to both BTV serotypes via blood meal and processed for histologic slides 10 days after infection. An in situ hybridization approach was employed using the RNAscope platform to detect the nucleic acid segment 2 of both serotypes. Observations of the mosaic patterns in which serotypes did not often overlap suggest that co-infection at the cellular level may not be abundant with these two serotypes in &lt;em&gt;C. sonorensis&lt;/em&gt;. This could be a consequence of superinfection exclusion. Understanding BTV co-infection and its biological consequences will add an important dimension to the modeling of viral evolution and emergence. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/09/30/Carpenter_RNA_scope_coinfection.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2023/09/30/Carpenter_RNA_scope_coinfection.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
