<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title> <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University </description><link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link> <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 10:11:37 -0600</pubDate> <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 10:11:37 -0600</lastBuildDate> <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator> <item><title>Xenosurveillance reflects traditional sampling techniques for the identification of human pathogens: A comparative study in West Africa</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;BACKGROUND:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Novel surveillance strategies are needed to detect the rapid and continuous emergence of infectious disease agents. Ideally, new sampling strategies should be simple to implement, technologically uncomplicated, and applicable to areas where emergence events are known to occur. To this end, xenosurveillance is a technique that makes use of blood collected by hematophagous arthropods to monitor and identify vertebrate pathogens. Mosquitoes are largely ubiquitous animals that often exist in sizable populations. As well, many domestic or peridomestic species of mosquitoes will preferentially take blood-meals from humans, making them a unique and largely untapped reservoir to collect human blood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="methodologyprincipal-findings"&gt;METHODOLOGY/PRINCIPAL FINDINGS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;We sought to take advantage of this phenomenon by systematically collecting blood-fed mosquitoes during a field trail in Northern Liberia to determine whether pathogen sequences from blood engorged mosquitoes accurately mirror those obtained directly from humans. Specifically, blood was collected from humans via finger-stick and by aspirating bloodfed mosquitoes from the inside of houses. Shotgun metagenomic sequencing of RNA and DNA derived from these specimens was performed to detect pathogen sequences. Samples obtained from xenosurveillance and from finger-stick blood collection produced a similar number and quality of reads aligning to two human viruses, GB virus C and hepatitis B virus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="conclusionssignificance"&gt;CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;This study represents the first systematic comparison between xenosurveillance and more traditional sampling methodologies, while also demonstrating the viability of xenosurveillance as a tool to sample human blood for circulating pathogens.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/03/21/Fauver_xenosurveillance.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/03/21/Fauver_xenosurveillance.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Divergent bornaviruses from Australian carpet pythons with neurological disease date the origin of extant Bornaviridae prior to the end-Cretaceous extinction.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tissue samples from Australian carpet pythons (Morelia spilota) with neurological disease were screened for viruses using next-generation sequencing. Coding complete genomes of two bornaviruses were identified with the gene order 3’-N-X-P-G-M-L, representing a transposition of the G and M genes compared to other bornaviruses and most mononegaviruses. Use of these viruses to search available vertebrate genomes enabled recognition of further endogenous bornavirus-like elements (EBLs) in diverse placental mammals, including humans. Codivergence patterns and shared integration sites revealed an ancestral laurasiatherian EBLG integration (77 million years ago [MYA]) and a previously identified afrotherian EBLG integration (83 MYA). The novel python bornaviruses clustered more closely with these EBLs than with other exogenous bornaviruses, suggesting that these viruses diverged from previously known bornaviruses prior to the end-Cretaceous (K-Pg) extinction, 66 MYA. It is possible that EBLs protected mammals from ancient bornaviral disease, providing a selective advantage in the recovery from the K-Pg extinction. A degenerate PCR primer set was developed to detect a highly conserved region of the bornaviral polymerase gene. It was used to detect 15 more genetically distinct bornaviruses from Australian pythons that represent a group that is likely to contain a number of novel species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="author-summary"&gt;Author summary&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike plants and animals, viruses don’t leave fossilised remains that can be used to study their ancient history. Rarely, however, some virus sequences end up as integrated copies in host genomes. These ‘fossilised’ virus sequences provide a window into virus evolution on a geological time scale. In this study, we identified bornaviruses in pythons, some of which had neurological disease. Bornaviruses have been associated with persistent neurological infections in a variety of mammalian and avian hosts. Here, we reveal that bornaviruses are associated with similar disease in reptiles as well. These new snake viruses turned out to be most closely related to bornavirus-like sequences that integrated into the DNA of mammals prior to the major extinction event at the end of the age of dinosaurs, the end-Cretaceous (K-Pg) extinction, 66 million years ago, allowing us to infer details of their prehistoric evolutionary history and origin. We also developed a test to detect these viruses from samples collected from live snakes, and used it to identify more related snake bornaviruses, indicating that this group will likely continue to expand.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/02/20/Hyndman_bornavirus.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/02/20/Hyndman_bornavirus.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Respiratory disease in ball pythons (Python regius) experimentally infected with ball python nidovirus</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Circumstantial evidence has linked a new group of nidoviruses with respiratory disease in pythons, lizards, and cattle. We conducted experimental infections in ball pythons (Python regius) to test the hypothesis that ball python nidovirus (BPNV) infection results in respiratory disease. Three ball pythons were inoculated orally and intratracheally with cell culture isolated BPNV and two were sham inoculated. Antemortem choanal, oroesophageal, and cloacal swabs and postmortem tissues of infected snakes were positive for viral RNA, protein, and infectious virus by qRT-PCR, immunohistochemistry, western blot and virus isolation. Clinical signs included oral mucosal reddening, abundant mucus secretions, open-mouthed breathing, and anorexia. Histologic lesions included chronic-active mucinous rhinitis, stomatitis, tracheitis, esophagitis and proliferative interstitial pneumonia. Control snakes remained negative and free of clinical signs throughout the experiment. Our findings establish a causal relationship between nidovirus infection and respiratory disease in ball pythons and shed light on disease progression and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="importance"&gt;Importance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past several years, nidovirus infection has been circumstantially linked to fatal respiratory disease in multiple python species, but a causal relationship has not been definitively established. Through experimental infections, our study fulfills Koch’s postulates and confirms ball python nidovirus as a primary respiratory pathogen in this species. Our findings will provide veterinarians valuable information for the diagnosis and management of this disease and lay the groundwork for continued scientific investigation of this sometimes fatal disease. Python nidoviruses are members of a growing group of viruses that have been associated with severe respiratory disease, including bovine nidovirus and shingleback lizard nidovirus. The establishment of BPNV as a primary pathogen in pythons is an important step in understanding the pathogenic potential of this emerging group of viruses.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/01/11/Hoon-Hanks_nidovirus.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/01/11/Hoon-Hanks_nidovirus.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Case Rodgers</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Case is a MIP major performing directed research in the lab. Case started spring semester 2018.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2018/01/10/case-rodgers.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2018/01/10/case-rodgers.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Nidovirus FAQ, 2018</title> <description>&lt;h1 id="snake-nidovirus-research-in-the-stenglein-lab"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snake Nidovirus Research in the Stenglein Lab&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Stenglein lab was among the first to discover nidoviruses in snakes and to link them to severe respiratory disease. Over the last 4 years, research on nidoviruses and their role in disease has continued in our laboratory. We have confirmed that nidoviruses cause respiratory disease in snakes and have made additional contributions to understanding the disease and how it is spread. Currently, we are focused on answering the following questions related to python nidoviruses:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;Which snake species are susceptible to infection?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Which snake species are susceptible to disease (some types of snakes may be infected but might not get sick)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;What fraction of infected snakes get sick, and to what extent?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Why do some types of snakes get infected but not others?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;How is infection transmitted from snake to snake?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Can some snakes recover from infection?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;How can infection best be diagnosed?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;What management strategies would be most effective at reducing or eliminating disease from a collection?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are pursuing a multi-pronged approach to answer these questions that relies on sampling of naturally-infected snakes in private collections, and laboratory experiments. We are particularly interested in sampling collections of mixed snakes species with a history of nidovirus-caused respiratory disease. &lt;strong&gt;We never disclose the identity of collections.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our laboratory does not currently study anti-viral therapies or vaccine development for this disease. There are several reasons for this: 1) similar respiratory viruses in humans and animals also lack effective therapeutics due to the nature of these viruses, 2) there are no effective commercially available vaccines for any diseases in snakes, and 3) these studies are usually very costly and often unsuccessful. We feel it is more practical and effective to investigate population characteristics of the disease in the hopes of generating appropriate management strategies for reduction and prevention of infection and spread.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1 id="frequently-asked-questions"&gt;Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h3 id="what-are-nidoviruses"&gt;What are nidoviruses?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nidoviruses are a group of related viruses known to cause a severe and sometimes fatal respiratory disease in snakes. These viruses are cousins of SARS and MERS coronaviruses that affect humans, which can also cause severe respiratory disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="what-snakes-are-susceptible-to-nidovirus-infection-and-disease"&gt;What snakes are susceptible to nidovirus infection and disease?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is one of the primary questions our laboratory is trying to answer. So far, nidoviruses have been detected predominately in pythons and some boas, but it is our goal to determine all the snake species that are susceptible and how severely the disease affects them. There is no evidence that this virus can infect or cause disease in humans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-many-strains-of-virus-are-there-and-how-do-they-differ-in-virulence"&gt;How many strains of virus are there and how do they differ in virulence?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Viruses that have complete genome sequencing data (a method for determining different strains of virus) have been isolated from ball pythons, an Indian rock python, and green tree pythons. The nidoviruses from ball and Indian rock pythons are relatively similar, but are quite different from those isolated from green tree pythons. Although these viruses have not been taxonomically categorized, it is likely there are multiple strains and these may affect snake species differently. Our research will attempt to address this question through the sampling of high numbers and a wide range of snakes of species.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="what-are-the-clinical-signs-of-nidovirus-infection"&gt;What are the clinical signs of nidovirus infection?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The clinical signs can vary from mild and non-specific to severe respiratory signs or sudden death. Typically, snakes will begin to have increased amounts of clear mucus in the mouth and nose (A) and the gums may become reddened. This can progress to wheezing, breathing with the mouth open (B), more rapid breathing, or coughing. Other signs include a poor or non-existent appetite, weight loss, decreased activity level, dehydration, and spending more time on the bottom of the cage (if a perching snake). Secondary bacterial infections may also play a role in disease, so mouth rot could be evidence of an underlying nidovirus infection (although there are many other causes for this as well).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-long-are-snakes-usually-infected"&gt;How long are snakes usually infected?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is currently unknown. Some snakes remain nidovirus positive for over a year. Other snakes succumb to disease and die within 6-12 months of being infected. There is also evidence in our laboratory that some snakes can clear the infection following 6-12 months of infection, but the data to support this remains anecdotal and this is not clearly established. Overall, this disease is chronic and usually results in long-term infection in snakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-is-this-disease-transmitted"&gt;How is this disease transmitted?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our laboratory has found virus in the oral/nasal cavity, lungs, and feces. Therefore, transmission is thought to occur by direct or indirect exposure to respiratory secretions (similar to the common cold) or to feces from infected snakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-can-nidovirus-infection-be-treated"&gt;How can nidovirus infection be treated?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, there is no specific treatment for nidovirus infection in snakes, nor is a vaccine available. This is similar to other viral diseases of snakes, and in fact in most species, including humans. Only rare viral diseases have been treated with anti-viral therapy and with varying success. Also, there are no effective commercially available vaccines for any snake diseases, despite attempts at vaccine production. Typical treatment includes supportive care and antibiotics to prevent secondary bacterial infections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-long-does-the-virus-stay-infectious-in-the-environment"&gt;How long does the virus stay infectious in the environment?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has not been tested for snake nidoviruses. However, SARS coronavirus, a closely related virus, is relatively stable outside of the host for up to 4 days. For SARS, heating and UV irradiation can eliminate infectious virus in the environment, as can common disinfectants (e.g. accelerated hydrogen peroxide, alcohol-based disinfectants with greater than 79% ethanol, and solutions with at least 0.050% of triclosan, 0.12% of Chloroxylenol (PCMX), 0.21% of sodium hypochlorite bleach, 0.23% of pine oil, or 0.10% of a quaternary compound with 79% of ethanol). It is unknown if snake nidoviruses are similarly affected by these disinfectant and antiseptic methods, but compounds listed above are good places to start when sterilizing cages and areas that have been exposed to nidovirus positive snakes or their excreta. These viruses may also be carried as fomites on hands, clothes, and instruments, therefore, it is important to use appropriate protective gear and washing of items before using between infected and uninfected snakes. Ideally, nidovirus positive snakes would be isolated/quarantined in a separate area and have designated instruments and protective gear only used with these snakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="where-can-i-find-recent-literature-about-snake-nidovirus"&gt;Where can I find recent literature about snake nidovirus?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stenglein 2014 - Ball Python Nidovirus: a Candidate Etiologic Agent for Severe Respiratory Disease in &lt;em&gt;Python regius&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;a href="http://mbio.asm.org/content/5/5/e01484-14.full?sid=31a8f271-30e1-44bf-b7e7-ef52710cdb11"&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;) (&lt;a href="/pdfs/papers/Stenglein_2014_mBio.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uccellini 2014 - Identification of a novel nidovirus in an outbreak of fatal respiratory disease in ball pythons (&lt;em&gt;Python regius&lt;/em&gt;). (&lt;a href="https://virologyj.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1743-422X-11-144"&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bodewes 2014 - Novel divergent nidovirus in a python with pneumonia. (&lt;a href="http://jgv.microbiologyresearch.org/content/journal/jgv/10.1099/vir.0.068700-0#tab2"&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marschang 2017 - Detection of nidoviruses in live pythons and boas. (&lt;a href="https://tpk.schattauer.de/en/contents/archive/issue/2453/manuscript/26682.html"&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dervas 2017 - Nidovirus-Associated Proliferative Pneumonia in the Green Tree Python (&lt;em&gt;Morelia viridis&lt;/em&gt;). (&lt;a href="http://jvi.asm.org/content/91/21/e00718-17.long"&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hoon-Hanks 2018 - Respiratory disease in ball pythons (&lt;em&gt;Python regius&lt;/em&gt;) experimentally infected with ball python nidovirus. (&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0042682217304130"&gt;Web&lt;/a&gt;) (&lt;a href="/pdfs/papers/Hoon-Hanks_2018_Virology.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="how-can-i-learn-more-about-the-stenglein-lab"&gt;How can I learn more about the Stenglein lab?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you would like to know more about the Stenglein lab and the research we do, or you believe you have a collection that might be suitable for our study, please don’t hesitate to contact us:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.stengleinlab.org/team/2014/09/29/mark-stenglein.html"&gt;Mark Stenglein&lt;/a&gt; - The head of the laboratory that conducts this research&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.stengleinlab.org/team/2015/05/11/laura-hoon-hanks.html"&gt;Laura Hoon-Hanks&lt;/a&gt; - The veterinary researcher in charge of the nidovirus project&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="what-can-i-do-to-support-this-research"&gt;What can I do to support this research?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We appreciate your support - please see below for donation instructions:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; # To financially support this research:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are interested in financially supporting our research, your support would be utilized in multiple ways:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;The purchase of snake sampling supplies (e.g. swabs, tubes, virus media) and the shipping costs, which we provide free-of-charge to the private collections we are studying.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The processing and testing of samples for nidovirus.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The analysis of nidovirus positive samples by multiple modalities to further characterize the virus and the disease it causes.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;No funds will be used to pay the researchers. This funding will go directly to supporting affected collections enrolled in the study and financing the experiments necessary to study this virus.*&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id="donation-instructions"&gt;Donation Instructions&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href="https://advancing.colostate.edu/CVMBS/MIP/GIVE"&gt;https://advancing.colostate.edu/CVMBS/MIP/GIVE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Enter the amount you would like to donate in the “Microbiology, Immunology &amp;amp; Pathology Department Research” field.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Click “Next”&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Enter in your contact information and click “Next”.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Select “Add Notes About My Gift” and enter “Stenglein lab nidovirus research” in the text field.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Proceed to payment information.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3 id="thank-you--we-appreciate-your-support"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thank you! We appreciate your support!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; </description> <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/12/19/Nidovirus_FAQ.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/12/19/Nidovirus_FAQ.html</guid> <category>blog</category> </item> <item><title>Metagenomic Investigation of Idiopathic Meningoencephalomyelitis in Dogs</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;BACKGROUND:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meningoencephalomyelitis of unknown origin (MUO) is a common and life-threatening neuroinflammatory disease in dogs. Features of the disease are suggestive of an underlying immune-mediated process, but the association of this disease with a pathogen is still unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="hypothesisobjectives"&gt;HYPOTHESIS/OBJECTIVES:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;To search for candidate etiologic agent associated with cases if MUO using next generation metagenomic sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="animals"&gt;ANIMALS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Twenty-two dogs diagnosed with either MUO (11/22; 10 CSF and 3 brain), or noninflammatory CNS diseases inconsistent with MUO (11/22; 11 CSF and 2 brain) that served as negative controls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="methods"&gt;METHODS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;A case control study was performed by identifying MUO and non-MUO cases. Samples were blindly processed and then unblinded for comparative analyses. Inclusion criteria for MUO cases included consistent MRI lesions and inflammatory CSF with a negative PCR panel for infectious agents or histopathologic diagnosis. Dogs with glucocorticoid therapy within 2 weeks of sample collection were excluded. Fresh-frozen cerebrospinal fluid (CSF; 21) and brain (5) samples were collected and RNA and DNA were extracted separately for shotgun metagenomic sequencing. Known positive samples were used as controls to validate our sequencing and analysis pipelines and to establish limits of detection. Sequencing results were analyzed at a nucleotide and protein level for broad comparison to known infectious organisms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="results"&gt;RESULTS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;No candidate etiologic agents were identified in dogs with MUO.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="conclusions-and-clinical-importance"&gt;CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL IMPORTANCE:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;These results support but do not prove the hypothesis that MUO is not associated with infectious agents and might be an autoimmune disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This work was a result of a great collaboration with veterinary neurologist &lt;a href="http://www.csuvth.colostate.edu/DirectorySearch/Search/MemberProfile/vth/1701/McGrath/Stephanie"&gt;Stephanie McGrath&lt;/a&gt;, who is a co-corresponding author.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/12/02/Hoon-Hanks_MUO.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/12/02/Hoon-Hanks_MUO.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Modeling the evolution of SIV sooty mangabey progenitor virus towards HIV-2 using humanized mice</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;HIV-2 is thought to have originated from an SIV progenitor native to sooty mangabeys. To model the initial human transmission and understand the sequential viral evolution, humanized mice were infected with SIVsm and serially passaged for five generations. Productive infection was seen by week 3 during the initial challenge followed by chronic viremia and gradual CD4+ T cell decline. Viral loads increased by the 5th generation resulting in more rapid CD4+ T cell decline. Genetic analysis revealed several amino acid substitutions that were nonsynonymous and fixed in multiple hu-mice across each of the 5 generations in the nef, env and rev regions. The highest rate of substitution occurred in the nef and env regions and most were observed within the first two generations. These data demonstrated the utility of hu-mice in modeling the SIVsm transmission to the human and to evaluate its potential sequential evolution into a human pathogen of HIV-2 lineage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;I assisted with data analysis for this work from the Akkina lab.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/10/01/Schmitt_SIV.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/10/01/Schmitt_SIV.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Lauren Kleine</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Lauren is an undergraduate student in the Biology department. Lauren started working in the lab in the Fall of 2017, and is focusing on computational projects.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/15/lauren-kleine.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/15/lauren-kleine.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Bernadette Maertens</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Bernadette is a student in the MIP &lt;a href="http://csu-cvmbs.colostate.edu/academics/mip/graduate/Pages/microbiology-immunology-professional-masters.aspx"&gt;MS-B professional masters program&lt;/a&gt;. Bernadette started working in the lab in the Fall of 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/11/bernadette-maertens.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/11/bernadette-maertens.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Amy Fox</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Amy is a student in the MIP &lt;a href="http://csu-cvmbs.colostate.edu/academics/mip/graduate/Pages/Microbiology-MS-and-PhD-Program.aspx"&gt;PhD program&lt;/a&gt; who rotated in the lab in the fall of 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/01/amy-fox.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/09/01/amy-fox.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> </channel> </rss>