<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title> <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University </description><link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link> <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 12:04:57 -0600</pubDate> <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 12:04:57 -0600</lastBuildDate> <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator> <item><title>Genomics of Disease in Wildlife Workshop, 2017</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://github.com/stenglein-lab/2017_GDW/"&gt;Link to workshop material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://gdwworkshop.colostate.edu/media/sites/131/2016/11/GDW.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to be participating in the inaugural &lt;a href="http://gdwworkshop.colostate.edu/"&gt;Genomics of Disease in Wildlife Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, which is being held starting today at Colorado State University. We just had our kick off reception, and I’m very impressed by the other instructors and the workshop participants. It seems like a great group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be leading several of the sections, on genomics, sequencing, accessing online resources, de novo assembly, and metagenomics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m putting all of the material (lectures, exercises) I’ve developed for this workshop up on GitHub, &lt;a href="http://github.com/stenglein-lab/2017_GDW/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/06/03/GDW_2017.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/06/03/GDW_2017.html</guid> <category>blog</category> </item> <item><title>Zach Osterholz</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Zach is a DVM student from the University of Illinois who worked in the lab in the summer of 2017 as a NIH-funded trainee in the Veterinary Summer Scholars Program. Zach setup our lab to work with live ticks, and performed pilot experiments investigating tick susceptibility to viral infection.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/zach-osterholz.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/zach-osterholz.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Mark Parlier</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Mark is a DVM student at CSU who started working in the lab in the summer of 2017 as a Merial scholar in the Veterinary Summer Scholars Program.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/mark-parlier.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/05/18/mark-parlier.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Differential disease susceptibility in experimentally reptarenavirus infected boa constrictors and ball pythons</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inclusion body disease (IBD) is an infectious disease originally described in captive snakes. It has traditionally been diagnosed by the presence of large eosinophilic cytoplasmic inclusions, and is associated with neurological, gastrointestinal and lymphoproliferative disorders. Previously, we identified and established a culture system for a novel lineage of arenaviruses isolated from boa constrictors diagnosed with IBD. Although ample circumstantial evidence suggested that these viruses, now known as reptarenaviruses, cause IBD, there has been no formal demonstration of disease causality since their discovery. We therefore conducted a long-term challenge experiment to test the hypothesis that reptarenaviruses cause IBD. We infected boa constrictors and ball pythons by cardiac injection of purified virus. We monitored progression of viral growth in tissues, blood, and environmental samples. Infection produced dramatically different disease outcomes in snakes of the two species. Ball pythons infected with Golden Gate virus (GoGV) and with another reptarenavirus displayed severe neurological signs within two months and viral replication was only detected in central nervous system tissues. In contrast, GoGV-infected boa constrictors remained free of clinical signs for two years despite high viral loads and the accumulation of large intracellular inclusions in multiple tissues including the brain. Inflammation was associated with infection in ball pythons but not in boa constrictors. Thus, reptarenavirus infection produces inclusions and inclusion body disease, although inclusions per se are neither necessarily associated with nor required for disease. Although the natural distribution of reptarenaviruses has yet to be described, the different outcome of infection may reflect differences in geographical origin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IMPORTANCE New DNA sequencing technologies have made it easier than ever to identify the sequences of microorganisms in diseased tissues, i.e. to identify organisms that appear to cause disease. But to be certain that a candidate pathogen actually causes disease, it is necessary to provide additional evidence of causality. We have done this to demonstrate that reptarenaviruses cause inclusion body disease (IBD), a serious transmissible disease of snakes. We infected boa constrictors and ball pythons with purified reptarenavirus. Ball pythons fell ill within two months of infection and displayed signs of neurological disease typical of IBD. In contrast, boa constrictors remained healthy over two years despite high levels of virus throughout their bodies. This difference matches previous reports that pythons are more susceptible to IBD than boas and could reflect the possibility that boas are natural hosts of these viruses in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h4&gt;</description> <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/05/16/Stenglein_IBD.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2017/05/16/Stenglein_IBD.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Nate Murcia</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Nate is an undergraduate MIP major. Nate started working in the lab in the Spring of 2017.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/04/11/nate-murcia.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2017/04/11/nate-murcia.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Shaun selected for a GAUSSI fellowship</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/team/2016/08/16/shaun-cross.html"&gt;Shaun&lt;/a&gt; has been selected to participate in the &lt;a href="http://gaussi.colostate.edu/"&gt;GAUSSI program&lt;/a&gt;. Congratulations, Shaun!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GAUSSI program at CSU is an NSF-funded program that aims to teach biologists more computing and computer scientists more biology. It offers 1-year fellowships to PhD students and a series of modular 1 and 2 credit &lt;a href="http://gaussi.colostate.edu/curriculum/fallcourses/"&gt;courses&lt;/a&gt; that allow trainees to pursue a tailored curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I co-teach a class in the GAUSSI program (with &lt;a href="http://csu-cvmbs.colostate.edu/academics/mip/Pages/Carol-Wilusz.aspx"&gt;Carol Wilusz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.biology.colostate.edu/people/dbsloan/"&gt;Dan Sloan&lt;/a&gt;), that teaches students how to design and perform experiments using next generation sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/04/07/shaun_Gaussi.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2017/04/07/shaun_Gaussi.html</guid> <category>blog</category> </item> <item><title>Development and Characterization of Recombinant Virus Generated from a New World Zika Virus Infectious Clone</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zika virus (ZIKV; family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus) is a rapidly expanding global pathogen that has been associated with severe clinical manifestations, including devastating neurological disease in infants. There are currently no molecular clones of a New World ZIKV available that lack significant attenuation, hindering progress toward understanding determinants of transmission and pathogenesis. Here we report the development and characterization of a novel ZIKV reverse genetics system based on a 2015 isolate from Puerto Rico (PRVABC59). We generated a two-plasmid infectious clone system from which infectious virus was rescued that replicates in human and mosquito cells with growth kinetics representative of wild-type ZIKV. Infectious clone-derived virus initiated infection and transmission rates in Aedes aegypti mosquitoes comparable to those of the primary isolate and displayed similar pathogenesis in AG129 mice. This infectious clone system provides a valuable resource to the research community to explore ZIKV molecular biology, vaccine development, antiviral development, diagnostics, vector competence, and disease pathogenesis.IMPORTANCE: ZIKV is a rapidly spreading mosquito-borne pathogen that has been linked to Guillain-Barré syndrome in adults and congenital microcephaly in developing fetuses and infants. ZIKV can also be sexually transmitted. The viral molecular determinants of any of these phenotypes are not well understood. There is no reverse genetics system available for the current epidemic virus that will allow researchers to study ZIKV immunity, develop novel vaccines, or develop antiviral drugs. Here we provide a novel infectious clone system generated from a recent ZIKV isolated from a patient infected in Puerto Rico. This infectious clone produces virus with in vitro and in vivo characteristics similar to those of the primary isolate, providing a critical tool to study ZIKV infection and disease.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Stenglein group had a minimal role in this nice paper from the &lt;a href="http://csu-cvmbs.colostate.edu/academics/mip/aidl/Pages/ebel-greg.aspx"&gt;Ebel lab&lt;/a&gt; and other groups at CSU and the CDC.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2016/12/16/Weger-Zika_clone.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2016/12/16/Weger-Zika_clone.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Detection and prevalence of boid inclusion body disease in collections of boas and pythons using immunological assays.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inclusion body disease (IBD) of boas and pythons is characterized by the intracytoplasmic accumulation of an antigenic 68 kDa viral protein IBDP, more recently known as the nucleoprotein (NP) of the reptarenaviruses. Blood samples of 131 captive boas and pythons (53 boa constrictors, Boa constrictor; 35 rainbow boas, Epicrates cenchria; 22 ball pythons, Python regius; 5 carpet pythons, Morelia spilota; 6 Burmese pythons, Python bivittatus; 4 Jamaican boas, Epicrates subflavus; 5 anacondas, Eunectes spp.; and 1 green tree python, Morelia viridis) were obtained from 28 collections in the USA. Diagnosis of IBD was initially made by the identification of eosinophilic intracytoplasmic inclusion bodies in hematoxylin and eosin (HE) stained blood films and isolated peripheral white blood cells (PWBC). The overall prevalence of IBD in study snakes was 25/131 or 19% (95% CI = 12.4%, 25.8%) with boa constrictors being more commonly infected (22/53 or 41.5%; 95% CI = 28.2%, 54.8%) than other species in this study. Of the 22 IBD positive boa constrictors, 87% were clinically healthy, 13% had various signs of chronic illness, and none showed signs of central nervous system disease. Using a validated monoclonal anti-NP antibody, NP was confirmed within the isolated PWBC by immunohistochemical staining and Western blots. The presence of reptarenaviruses within blood samples of 27 boa constrictors and three rainbow boas was also assessed by PCR. Among boa constrictors, very good agreements were shown between the observation of inclusion bodies (by HE stain) and the presence of NP (by immunohistochemistry, kappa = 0.92; and Western blots, kappa = 0.89), or the presence of reptarenaviruses (by PCR; kappa = 0.92).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id="comment"&gt;Comment&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper was largely the work of Rita Chang and Elliott Jacobson, who literally wrote &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Infectious-Diseases-Pathology-Reptiles-Color/dp/0849323215"&gt;the textbook&lt;/a&gt; on reptile infectious diseases. We contributed by assessing reptarenavirus prevalence using PCR.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2016/10/29/Chang_IBD.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2016/10/29/Chang_IBD.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Lauren Kuechler</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Lauren is a CSU undergraduate Biomedical Sciences major who has been volunteering in the lab since 2016, contributing to our studies on snake viruses.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2016/10/27/lauren-kuechler.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2016/10/27/lauren-kuechler.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Possibility and Challenges of Conversion of Current Virus Species Names to Linnaean Binomials</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Botanical, mycological, zoological, and prokaryotic species names follow the Linnaean format, consisting of an italicized Latinized binomen with a capitalized genus name and a lower-case species epithet (e.g., &lt;em&gt;Homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt;). Virus species names, however, do not follow a uniform format, and even when binomial, are not Linnaean in style. In this thought exercise, we attempted to convert all currently official names of species included in the virus family &lt;em&gt;Arenaviridae&lt;/em&gt; and the virus order &lt;em&gt;Mononegavirales&lt;/em&gt; to Linnaean binomials, and to identify and address associated challenges and concerns. Surprisingly, this endeavor was not as complicated or time-consuming as even the authors of this article expected when conceiving the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2016/10/22/Kuhn-binomials.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2016/10/22/Kuhn-binomials.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> </channel> </rss>