<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>Welcome to the Stenglein Lab</title> <description>This is the website of the Stenglein Lab at Colorado State University </description><link>http://stengleinlab.org/</link> <atom:link href="http://stengleinlab.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 17:27:25 -0700</pubDate> <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 17:27:25 -0700</lastBuildDate> <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator> <item><title>There is no existing good evidence that 2019-nCoV originated in snakes.</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/JMV.25682"&gt;A paper&lt;/a&gt; published online on Jan 20, 2020 in the Journal of Medical Virology, titled &lt;em&gt;Homologous recombination within the spike glycoprotein of the newly identified coronavirus 2019-nCoV may boost cross-species transmission from snake to human&lt;/em&gt; raises the intriguing possibility that a new coronavirus of substantial public health concern may have originated in snakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This new coronavirus, named 2019-nCoV, has infected and caused disease in several hundred people, mainly in Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China. Public health officials are appropriately concerned about this new human pathogen, and the CDC provides a great English language situation summary, &lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-nCoV/summary.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/JMV.25682"&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, the authors make two primary claims. First, that 2019-nCoV is a recombinant virus. Second, that “…our evolutionary analysis suggest for the first time that snake is the most probable wildlife animal reservoir for the 2019-nCoV.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recombination occurs when two viruses exchange genetic material. I’m not going to evaluate the claim that this virus may be recombinant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will however, consider the evidence that this virus may have originally been transmitted to humans from snakes. As I describe below, there is no direct evidence to support this claim, and the indirect evidence is flimsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many pathogens can be transmitted from other animals to humans. Snakes were apparently one of the types of animals sold at the seafood market that has been linked to many of the initial human cases of 2019-nCoV. So it is plausible that this virus could have been from snakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no direct evidence that this type of coronavirus infects snakes. The authors do not identify a similar virus in snakes, and no similar coronaviruses have been identified previously in snakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(My lab &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01484-14"&gt;has&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2017.12.008"&gt;studied&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2019.00338"&gt;respiratory viruses&lt;/a&gt; of snakes that are belong to the same umbrella virus group as 2019-nCoV, but these are distant relatives).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main line of evidence the authors present to support the claim that this virus may have originated in snakes is indirect, and based on codon usage patterns. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_code"&gt;Codons&lt;/a&gt; are DNA base triplets that encode a single amino acid in a protein. The same amino acid may be encoded by different codons, so there is flexibility in how a particular protein sequence could be encoded. Different organisms tend to use codons in a characteristic way. Viruses that matched their codon usage to that of their host could have an evolutionary advantage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So if, as seems likely, 2019-nCoV was recently transmitted to humans from other animals, then it might be possible to discern the original host by comparing codon usage patterns of the virus to candidate hosts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The authors compare the codon usage signatures of 2019-nCoV with several candidate hosts, corresponding to some of the animals that were sold in the seafood market that has been linked to this outbreak and to the most closely related cornavirus to 2019-nCoV, bat-SL-CoVZC45, which was identified in a &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/MG772933.1"&gt;bat in 2017&lt;/a&gt;. The authors then compare these frequencies using a metric, the squared Euclidian distance, as a measure of how similar these codon usage patterns are between the various species. The results are shown in figure 3 of the paper:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/figure_3.png" alt="Figure 3" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The “heatmap” in panel A depicts the frequencies with which codons are used in different organisms. Each column of the table is one organism. Each row is one of 61 possible codons. A redder color indicates that a particular codon is used more often in that organism. A green color means that codon is used less frequently. The heirarchical branching at the top of the figure indicates the extent to which these patterns are similar in different species. You can see that the two similar viruses (the two left-most columns) have closely related codon usage patterns, as expected. The two snakes have relatively similar patterns, and the mammals have similar patterns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The claim that snakes are the “most probable wildlife” origin of 2019-nCoV rest on the bar graph shown in panel B which shows the similarity, measured by Euclidian distance, between the codon usage pattern of 2019-nCoV and the various possible hosts. The distance between 2019-nCoV and the 2 snakes is ~12-15, whereas the distance between that virus and the mammals is &amp;gt;25. At first glance, this seems convincing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But consider the case of the other coronavirus analyzed, bat-SL-CoVZC45. This virus was isolated from a &lt;a href="http://www.bio.bris.ac.uk/research/bats/China%20bats/rhinolophussinicus.htm"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rhinolophus sinicus&lt;/em&gt; bat&lt;/a&gt; in China in 2017. It’s codon usage pattern is essentially identical to that of 2019-nCoV. Consequently, the distances between it’s codon usage pattern and the candidate hosts will be essentially identical to those shown in panel B. &lt;strong&gt;By the logic presented here, the bat-SL-CoVZC45 virus, from a &lt;em&gt;Rhinolophus sinicus&lt;/em&gt; bat, is more likely to have originated from a snake than from a &lt;em&gt;Rhinolophus sinicus&lt;/em&gt; bat.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the absence of direct evidence that this type of coronavirus can infect snakes, it is possible to imagine a scenario where previously unknown snake coronaviruses independently transmitted to bats and to humans. &lt;strong&gt;But in my opinion, a simpler and more likely explanation is that this kind of codon usage analysis has limited predictive value to pinpoint a virus’s exact host in a situation like this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It remains possible that snakes are the source of 2019-nCoV, but the data presented here is not convincing evidence of that.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2020/01/22/did-the-new-coronavirus-come-from-snakes.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/blog/2020/01/22/did-the-new-coronavirus-come-from-snakes.html</guid> <category>blog</category> </item> <item><title>Tillie Dunham</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Tillie is an MIP major performing directed research in the lab on viruses in arthropod model organisms and disease vectors. Tillie started spring semester 2019.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/tillie-dunham.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/tillie-dunham.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>Landon Basner</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Landon is an MIP major performing directed research in the lab on bunyaviruses and working in the NGS facility. Landon started spring semester 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/landon-basner.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/team/2019/01/30/landon-basner.html</guid> <category>team</category> </item> <item><title>The expectations and challenges of wildlife disease research in the era of genomics: forecasting with a horizon scan-like exercise</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The outbreak and transmission of disease-causing pathogens are contributing to the unprecedented rate of biodiversity decline. Recent advances in genomics have coalesced into powerful tools to monitor, detect, and reconstruct the role of pathogens impacting wildlife populations. Wildlife researchers are thus uniquely positioned to merge ecological and evolutionary studies with genomic technologies to exploit unprecedented ‘Big Data’ tools in disease research; however, many researchers lack the training and expertise required to use these computationally intensive methodologies. To address this disparity, the inaugural ‘Genomics of Disease in Wildlife’ workshop assembled early to mid-career professionals with expertise across scientific disciplines (e.g., genomics, wildlife biology, veterinary sciences, and conservation management) for training in the application of genomic tools to wildlife disease research. A horizon scanning-like exercise, an activity to identify forthcoming trends and challenges, performed by the workshop participants identified and discussed five themes considered to be the most pressing to the application of genomics in wildlife disease research: i) “Improving Communication”, ii) “Methodological and Analytical Advancements”, iii) “Translation into Practice”, iv) “Integrating Landscape Ecology and Genomics”, and v) “Emerging New Questions”. Wide-ranging solutions from the horizon scan were international in scope, itemized both deficiencies and strengths in wildlife genomic initiatives, promoted the use of genomic technologies to unite wildlife and human disease research, and advocated best practices for optimal use of genomic tools in wildlife disease projects. The results offer a glimpse of the potential revolution in human and wildlife disease research possible through multi-disciplinary collaborations at local, regional, and global scales.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2019/01/12/Fitak_Horizon_Scan.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2019/01/12/Fitak_Horizon_Scan.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Strengthening the Interaction of the Virology Community with the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) by Linking Virus Names and Their Abbreviations to Virus Species</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) is tasked with classifying viruses into taxa (phyla to species) and devising taxon names. Virus names and virus name abbreviations are currently not within the ICTV’s official remit and are not regulated by an official entity. Many scientists, medical/veterinary professionals, and regulatory agencies do not address evolutionary questions nor are they concerned with the hierarchical organization of the viral world, and therefore, have limited use for ICTV-devised taxa. Instead, these professionals look to the ICTV as an expert point source that provides the most current taxonomic affiliations of viruses of interests to facilitate document writing. These needs are currently unmet as an ICTV-supported, easily searchable database that includes all published virus names and abbreviations linked to their taxa is not available. In addition, in stark contrast to other biological taxonomic frameworks, virus taxonomy currently permits individual species to have several members. Consequently, confusion emerges among those who are not aware of the difference between taxa and viruses, and because certain well-known viruses cannot be located in ICTV publications or be linked to their species. In addition, the number of duplicate names and abbreviations has increased dramatically in the literature. To solve this conundrum, the ICTV could mandate listing all viruses of established species and all reported unclassified viruses in forthcoming online ICTV Reports and create a searchable webpage using this information. The International Union of Microbiology Societies could also consider changing the mandate of the ICTV to include the nomenclature of all viruses in addition to taxon considerations. With such a mandate expansion, official virus names and virus name abbreviations could be catalogued and virus nomenclature could be standardized. As a result, the ICTV would become an even more useful resource for all stakeholders in virology.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/31/Calisher_virus_names.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/31/Calisher_virus_names.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>A reverse-transcription/RNase H based protocol for depletion of mosquito ribosomal RNA facilitates viral intrahost evolution analysis, transcriptomics and pathogen discovery.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identifying novel viruses or assessing viral variation by NGS requires high sequencing coverage. More than 90% of total RNA is ribosomal (rRNA), making variant calling, virus discovery or transcriptomic profiling difficult. Current methods to increase informative reads suffer from drawbacks, either they cannot be used for some viruses, are optimized for a single species, or introduce bias. We describe a two-part approach combining reverse-transcription to create RNA/DNA hybrids which are then degraded with RNaseH/DNase sequentially that works for three medically relevant mosquito genera; Aedes, Anopheles, and Culex. We demonstrate depletion of rRNA from different samples, including whole mosquitoes and midgut contents from FTA cards. We describe novel insect-specific virus genomes from field collected mosquitoes. The protocol requires only common laboratory reagents and small oligonucleotides specific to rRNA. This approach can be adapted for other organisms, aiding virus diversity analyses, virus discovery and transcriptomics in both laboratory and field samples.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/30/Fauver_RNaseH.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/12/30/Fauver_RNaseH.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Ebola virus, but not Marburg virus, replicates efficiently and without required adaptation in snake cells.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ebola virus (EBOV) disease is a viral hemorrhagic fever with a high case-fatality rate in humans. This disease is caused by four members of the filoviral genus Ebolavirus, including EBOV. The natural hosts reservoirs of ebolaviruses remain to be identified. Glycoprotein 2 of reptarenaviruses, known to infect only boa constrictors and pythons, is similar in sequence and structure to ebolaviral glycoprotein 2, suggesting that EBOV may be able to infect reptilian cells. Therefore, we serially passaged EBOV and a distantly related filovirus, Marburg virus (MARV), in boa constrictor JK cells and characterized viral infection/replication and mutational frequency by confocal imaging and sequencing. We observed that EBOV efficiently infected and replicated in JK cells, but MARV did not. In contrast to most cell lines, EBOV-infected JK cells did not result in an obvious cytopathic effect. Surprisingly, genomic characterization of serial-passaged EBOV in JK cells revealed that genomic adaptation was not required for infection. Deep sequencing coverage (&amp;gt;10,000×) demonstrated the existence of only a single nonsynonymous variant (EBOV glycoprotein precursor pre-GP T544I) of unknown significance within the viral population that exhibited a shift in frequency of at least 10 per cent over six serial passages. In summary, we present the first reptilian cell line that replicates a filovirus at high titers, and for the first time demonstrate a filovirus genus-specific restriction to MARV in a cell line. Our data suggest the possibility that there may be differences between the natural host spectra of ebolaviruses and marburgviruses.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/11/28/Fedewa_Ebola.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/11/28/Fedewa_Ebola.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Co-Infection Patterns in Individual Ixodes scapularis Ticks Reveal Associations between Viral, Eukaryotic and Bacterial Microorganisms</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ixodes scapularis&lt;/em&gt; ticks harbor a variety of microorganisms, including eukaryotes, bacteria and viruses. Some of these can be transmitted to and cause disease in humans and other vertebrates. Others are not pathogenic, but may impact the ability of the tick to harbor and transmit pathogens. A growing number of studies have examined the influence of bacteria on tick vector competence but the influence of the tick virome remains less clear, despite a surge in the discovery of tick-associated viruses. In this study, we performed shotgun RNA sequencing on 112 individual adult &lt;em&gt;I. scapularis&lt;/em&gt; collected in Wisconsin, USA. We characterized the abundance, prevalence and co-infection rates of viruses, bacteria and eukaryotic microorganisms. We identified pairs of tick-infecting microorganisms whose observed co-infection rates were higher or lower than would be expected, or whose RNA levels were positively correlated in co-infected ticks. Many of these co-occurrence and correlation relationships involved two bunyaviruses, South Bay virus and blacklegged tick phlebovirus-1. These viruses were also the most prevalent microorganisms in the ticks we sampled, and had the highest average RNA levels. Evidence of associations between microbes included a positive correlation between RNA levels of South Bay virus and &lt;em&gt;Borrelia burgdorferi&lt;/em&gt;, the Lyme disease agent. These findings contribute to the rationale for experimental studies on the impact of viruses on tick biology and vector competence.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/07/22/Cross_tick_metagenome.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/07/22/Cross_tick_metagenome.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Adventitious viruses persistently infect three commonly used mosquito cell lines.</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mosquito cell lines have been used extensively in research to isolate and propagate arthropod-borne viruses and understand virus-vector interactions. Despite their utility as an in vitro tool, these cell lines are poorly defined and may harbor insect-specific viruses. Accordingly, we screened four commonly-used mosquito cell lines, C6/36 and U4.4 cells from Aedes albopictus, Aag2 cells from Aedes aegypti, and Hsu cells from Culex quinquefasciatus, for the presence of adventitious (i.e. exogenous) viruses. All four cell lines stained positive for double-stranded RNA, indicative of RNA virus replication. We subsequently identified viruses infecting Aag2, U4.4 and Hsu cell lines using untargeted next-generation sequencing, but not C6/36 cells. PCR confirmation revealed that these sequences stem from active viral replication and/or integration into the cellular genome. Our results show that these commonly-used mosquito cell lines are persistently-infected with several viruses. This finding may be critical to interpreting data generated in these systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description> <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/06/26/Weger-Lucarelli_mosquito_cell_viruses.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/06/26/Weger-Lucarelli_mosquito_cell_viruses.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> <item><title>Xenosurveillance reflects traditional sampling techniques for the identification of human pathogens: A comparative study in West Africa</title> <description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="background"&gt;BACKGROUND:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Novel surveillance strategies are needed to detect the rapid and continuous emergence of infectious disease agents. Ideally, new sampling strategies should be simple to implement, technologically uncomplicated, and applicable to areas where emergence events are known to occur. To this end, xenosurveillance is a technique that makes use of blood collected by hematophagous arthropods to monitor and identify vertebrate pathogens. Mosquitoes are largely ubiquitous animals that often exist in sizable populations. As well, many domestic or peridomestic species of mosquitoes will preferentially take blood-meals from humans, making them a unique and largely untapped reservoir to collect human blood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="methodologyprincipal-findings"&gt;METHODOLOGY/PRINCIPAL FINDINGS:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;We sought to take advantage of this phenomenon by systematically collecting blood-fed mosquitoes during a field trail in Northern Liberia to determine whether pathogen sequences from blood engorged mosquitoes accurately mirror those obtained directly from humans. Specifically, blood was collected from humans via finger-stick and by aspirating bloodfed mosquitoes from the inside of houses. Shotgun metagenomic sequencing of RNA and DNA derived from these specimens was performed to detect pathogen sequences. Samples obtained from xenosurveillance and from finger-stick blood collection produced a similar number and quality of reads aligning to two human viruses, GB virus C and hepatitis B virus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="conclusionssignificance"&gt;CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE:&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;This study represents the first systematic comparison between xenosurveillance and more traditional sampling methodologies, while also demonstrating the viability of xenosurveillance as a tool to sample human blood for circulating pathogens.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate><link>http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/03/21/Fauver_xenosurveillance.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://stengleinlab.org/papers/2018/03/21/Fauver_xenosurveillance.html</guid> <category>papers</category> </item> </channel> </rss>